A Guide to the Minutes of the Virginia State Board of Education, 1870-2003
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Minutes of the Virginia State Board of Education, 1870-2003
The Library of Virginia
31643, 31755, 31838, 32864, 33407, 41254, 43481
41.9 cu. ft. (47 boxes and 57 volumes)
Virginia. State Board of Education.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred on an unknown date from the Virginia State Board of Education [Acc. 31643].
Transferred on 29 April 1983 from the Virginia State Board of Education [Acc. 31755].
Transferred on an unknown date from the Virginia State Board of Education [Acc. 31838].
Transferred on 25 November 1986 from the Virginia State Board of Education [Acc. 32864].
Transferred on 10 February 1989 from the Virginia State Board of Education [Acc. 33407].
Transferred on 15 June 2004 from the Virginia State Board of Education [Acc. 41254].
Transferred on 12 October 2007 from the Virginia State Board of Education [Acc. 43481].
Biographical Information
The development of the Dept. of Education began in 1870 when Dr. William H. Ruffner was elected by the General Assembly to be the first Superintendent of Public Instruction. At the end of its first 50 years, the department had less than 20 staff members. In 1928, the Superintendent was first appointed by the governor. Staff size was expanded to in order to meet the increased need for services including the purchase of textbooks, libraries, and general buildings services. The Commonwealth of Virginia is divided into school divisions, each of which has a school board. Each locality appoints a Division Superintendent using criteria established by the State Board of Education.The mission of Virginia's public education system is to educate students in the fundamental knowledge and academic subjects that they need to become capable, responsible, and self-reliant citizens. The mission of the Virginia Board of Education and the Superintendent of Public Instruction, in cooperation with local school boards, is to increase student learning and academic achievement.
The mission of Virginia's public education system is to educate students in the fundamental knowledge and academic subjects that they need to become capable, responsible, and self-reliant citizens. The mission of the Virginia Board of Education and the Superintendent of Public Instruction, in cooperation with local school boards, is to increase student learning and academic achievement.
The Department of Education has responsibilities in adult education, teacher certification, financial assistance, and administrative and advisory services to school divisions. The Department is operated by a superintendent who is appointed by the governor. The Department's activities are supervised by a Board of Education, which consists of nine members appointed by the Governor. The Board of Education is the governing and policy-making body for the Virginia system of public elementary and secondary education. It focuses on accountability, evaluation, state testing and assessment programs, curriculum, and teacher education. The Superintendent of Public Instruction serves as Secretary of the Board.
Scope and Content
Official minutes, 1870-2003, of the Virginia State Board of Education. Minutes for 1870-1977 are in bound volumes, while later minutes are loose. Minutes not in volume format also include agendas, finances, and supporting documentation used by Board members. Of note are the index cards for the minutes, ca. 1930-1980, in Acc. 31755 [Series II].
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I: Minutes, 1870-1970 [Acc. 31643]
Series II: Minutes, ca. 1930-1980 [Acc. 31755]
Series III: Minutes, 1971-1977 [Acc. 31838]
Series IV: Minutes, 1981-1985 [Acc. 32864]
Series V: Minutes, 1986-1987 [Acc. 33407]
Series VI: Minutes, 1980-1996 [Acc. 41254]
Series VII: Minutes, 1998-2002 [Acc. 43481]
Contents List
- Series I: Minutes, 1870-1970 [Acc. 31643]., Extent: 4.9 cu. ft. (49 volumes). (Volume 1-49)
  - Minutes, 1870-1873 (Volume 1)
  - Minutes, 1873-1886 (Volume 2)
  - Minutes, 1902 Jan-1912 May (Volume 3)
  - Minutes, 1904-1915 (Volume 4)
  - Minutes, 1912 May-1917 Sept (Volume 5)
  - Minutes, 1917 Nov-1919 Sept (Volume 6)
  - Minutes, 1920-1929 (Volume 7)
  - Minutes, 1930 (Volume 8)
  - Minutes, 1931 (Volume 9)
  - Minutes, 1932 (Volume 10)
  - Minutes, 1933 (Volume 11)
  - Minutes, 1934 (Volume 12)
  - Minutes (special meeting), 1934 February (Volume 13)
  - Minutes, 1935 (Volume 14)
  - Minutes, 1936 (Volume 15)
  - Minutes, 1937 (Volume 16)
  - Minutes, 1938 (Volume 17)
  - Minutes, 1939 (Volume 18)
  - Minutes, 1940 (Volume 19)
  - Minutes, 1941 (Volume 20)
  - Minutes, 1942 (Volume 21)
  - Minutes, 1943 (Volume 22)
  - Minutes, 1944 (Volume 23)
  - Minutes, 1945 (Volume 24)
  - Minutes, 1946 (Volume 25)
  - Minutes, 1947 (Volume 26)
  - Minutes, 1948 (Volume 27)
  - Minutes, 1949 (Volume 28)
  - Minutes, 1950 (Volume 29)
  - Minutes, 1951 (Volume 30)
  - Minutes, 1952 (Volume 31)
  - Minutes, 1953 (Volume 32)
  - Minutes, 1954 (Volume 33)
  - Minutes, 1955 (Volume 34)
  - Minutes, 1956 (Volume 35)
  - Minutes, 1957 (Volume 36)
  - Minutes, 1958 (Volume 37)
  - Minutes, 1959 (Volume 38)
  - Minutes, 1960 (Volume 39)
  - Minutes, 1961 (Volume 40)
  - Minutes, 1962 (Volume 41)
  - Minutes, 1963 (Volume 42)
  - Minutes, 1964 (Volume 43)
  - Minutes, 1965 (Volume 44)
  - Minutes, 1966 (Volume 45)
  - Minutes, 1967 (Volume 46)
  - Minutes, 1968 (Volume 47)
  - Minutes, 1969 (Volume 48)
  - Minutes, 1970 (Volume 49)
- Series II: Minutes, ca. 1930-1980 [Acc. 31755]., Extent: 3.2 cu. ft. (14 boxes). (Box 1-14)
  - Index to Minute Books 1-35, ca. 1930-1964 (Box 1-12)
  - Minutes, 1978-1979 (Box 13)
  - Minutes, 1980 (Box 14)
- Series III: Minutes, 1971-1977 [Acc. 31838]., Extent: .8 cu. ft. (8 volumes). (Volume 50-57)
  - Minutes, 1971 (Volume 50)
  - Minutes, 1972 (Volume 51)
  - Minutes, 1973 January-June (Volume 52)
  - Minutes, 1973 July-December (Volume 53)
  - Minutes, 1974 (Volume 54)
  - Minutes, 1975 (Volume 55)
  - Minutes, 1976 (Volume 56)
  - Minutes, 1977 (Volume 57)
- Series IV: Minutes, 1981-1985 [Acc. 32864]., Extent: 1 cu. ft. (1 box). (Box 1)
  - Minutes, 1981-1985 (Box 1)
- Series V: Minutes, 1986-1987 [Acc. 33407]., Extent: 1 box. (Box 1)
  - Minutes, 1986-1987 (Box 1)
- Series VI: Minutes, 1971-2003 [Acc. 41254]., Extent: 26 cu. ft. (26 boxes). (Box 1-26)
  - Minutes, 1980 May-December (Box 1)
  - Minutes, 1981 (Box 2)
  - Minutes, 1981 (Box 3)
  - Minutes, 1982 (Box 4)
  - Minutes, 1982-1986 (Box 5)
  - Minutes, 1983 (Box 6)
  - Minutes, 1983 (Box 7)
  - Minutes, 1984 (Box 8)
  - Minutes, 1985 January-November (Box 9)
  - Minutes, 1987 January-November (Box 10)
  - Minutes, 1987-1988 August (Box 11)
  - Minutes, 1988 September-December (Box 12)
  - Minutes, 1989 May-November (Box 13)
  - Minutes, 1989 January-April (Box 14)
  - Minutes, 1990 January-May (Box 15)
  - Minutes, 1990 June-November (Box 16)
  - Minutes, 1991 August-December (Box 17)
  - Minutes, 1991 January-June (Box 18)
  - Minutes, 1992 February-October (Box 19)
  - Minutes, 1993 (Box 20)
  - Minutes, 1994 (Box 21)
  - Minutes, 1995 (Box 22)
  - Minutes, 1996 (Box 23)
  - Minutes, 1997 January-July (Box 24)
  - Minutes, 1997 September-November (Box 25)
  - Minutes (microfiche), 1971-2003 (Box 26)
- Series VII: Minutes, 1998-2002 [Acc. 43481]., Extent: 5 cu. ft. (5 boxes). (Box 1-5)
  - Minutes, 1998 January-November (Box 1)
  - Minutes, 1999 January-November (Box 2)
  - Minutes, 2000 January-November (Box 3)
  - Minutes, 2001 January-November (Box 4)
  - Minutes, 2002 January-November (Box 5)